<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The divine authority of the Holy Scriptures asserted in two discourses the former shewing the nature and extent of the inspiration vouchsaf't by the Holy Ghost to the penmen of the Scriptures ... : the latter shewing the divine authority of the vowels and accents in the Hebrew text ... in a discourse concerning the division of the Bible into chapters and verses : to which is added, A discourse concerning the testimony of the Spirit on Rom. 8. 16. / by Sam. Clark ...</title>
            <author>Clark, Samuel, 1626-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4991_CANCELLED</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14562</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11713877</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11713877</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33290)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 21:12 or 1882:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The divine authority of the Holy Scriptures asserted in two discourses the former shewing the nature and extent of the inspiration vouchsaf't by the Holy Ghost to the penmen of the Scriptures ... : the latter shewing the divine authority of the vowels and accents in the Hebrew text ... in a discourse concerning the division of the Bible into chapters and verses : to which is added, A discourse concerning the testimony of the Spirit on Rom. 8. 16. / by Sam. Clark ...</title>
                  <author>Clark, Samuel, 1626-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [14].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy at reel 21:12 contains only the first discourse; copy at reel 1882:21 contains only the second discourse, "Exercitations concerning the original of the chapters and verses in the Bible. London, 1698". Neither copy contains the third part, "Discourse concerning the testimony of the Spirit."</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 1882:21 is identified as Wing C4491 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Harvard University Libraries and British LIbrary.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Evidences, authority, etc.</term>
               <term>Holy Spirit.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Divine Authority OF THE HOLY SCRIPTURES Aſſerted in Two DISCOURSES: The former ſhewing The Nature and Extent of the Inſpiration vouchſaf't by the Holy Ghoſt to the Penmen of the Scriptures, and the diſtinct ſhare of each therein.</p>
            <p>The latter ſhewing the Divine Authority of the Vowels and Accents in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text; by new and intrinſick Arguments: in a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning the Diviſion of the Bible into Chapters and Verſes.</p>
            <p>To which is added, A Diſcourſe concerning the Teſtimony of the Spirit on <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAM. CLARK,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Lyon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:39375:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39375:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>WHAT Aſſaults have bin made of late Years upon the <hi>Divine Authority</hi> of the Holy Scriptures, is not unknown to thoſe that think it their concern to attend unto ſuch matters. This was done more cloſely and covertly divers Years ago by <hi>F. Simon</hi> in his <hi>Critical Hiſtory of the Old Teſtament:</hi> In reference to which, that very Learned and Judicious Divine Mr. <hi>W. Lorimer,</hi> hath tranſlated and publiſht, <hi>A Vindication of the five Books of</hi> Moſes, with an <hi>Appendix</hi> of his own, in Anſwer to <hi>F. Simon</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions. A more open Attack was made upon it by the Author of the <hi>five Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:</hi> Theſe were firſt anſwer'd among
<pb facs="tcp:39375:3"/> us by Mr. <hi>Louth,</hi> an ingenious Member of the famous Univerſity of <hi>Oxford.</hi> I was much pleas'd with the Candour of a paſſage in his <hi>Preface: In the laſt place,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I muſt deſire of thoſe, who think I have not carried the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of the Scriptures ſo high as I ought, not to be angry with me, or uncharitably to cenſure me, as if I deſign'd to betray the Cauſe which I pretend to maintain; but if they are not ſatisfied with my performance, to undertake the Argument them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and do Juſtice to ſo good a Cauſe: I aſſure them, I ſhall heartily wiſh 'em Succeſs in their Undertaking, and ſhall be glad if my Arguments appear weak, becauſe their's are ſtronger: for</hi> I can do nothing againſt the Truth, but for the Truth, <hi>p. 16.</hi> After him comes Mr. <hi>La Mothe,</hi> who takes notice of that paſſage, and makes uſe of it as an Invitation to his Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: and withal adds, <hi>If my Example ſhould excite ſome others— to write
<pb facs="tcp:39375:3"/> upon the ſame Subject, the Publick will be oblig'd to me for it.</hi> In that Diſcourſe of his, he hath fully and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorily Vindicated the Divine <hi>Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the <hi>Books of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament:</hi> ſo that thoſe <hi>Letters</hi> may be diſmiſs'd from any further Conſideration, being ſolidly and fully anſwer'd.</p>
            <p>But as to what Mr. <hi>La Mothe</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers concerning the Nature of that Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I am not ſo well ſatisfied: It ſeemed to me very defective, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited me to ſeek after further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Whereupon I peruſed all thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors (within the compaſs of my <hi>Curta ſupellex</hi>) wherein I might reaſonably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to have met with ſomething that might have quench'd my Thirſt, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with my Pitcher empty: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I fell a plowing with my own Heifer, and that which follows is the Crop which the Reader may reap, if he thinks it worth while to beſtow ſo much pains upon it. And this I intend only as <hi>Cumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:39375:4"/> to what is deliver'd by Mr. <hi>Louth,</hi> and <hi>La Mothe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this late debate, there has bin another Controverſy of longer ſtanding, which has bin hotly canvaſt and conteſted <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> between the moſt learned Pens on both ſides, which has a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the divine Authority of the holy Scriptures alſo, <hi>viz.</hi> about the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of the <hi>Vowels</hi> and <hi>Accents</hi> in the Hebrew Text of the Old Teſtament. Much confidence (or, according to modiſh word, Aſſurance) has bin ſhow'd on both ſides. This point was ſtudied by me when I was in the Univerſity above fifty Years ago: And ſince then I have bin looking into what I met with on that ſubject. Of late I have beſtow'd ſome thoughts upon it upon this occaſion. Being deſired to draw up <hi>A brief Concordance</hi> to be added to the third Edition of Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s Annotations I intended to Preface it, with an <hi>Account of the Diviſion of the Bible into Chapters and Verſes,</hi> the foundation of all exact Concordances, and without
<pb facs="tcp:39375:4"/> which they cannot but be very lame and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective. Thereupon making Enquiry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Original of the <hi>Chapters</hi> and <hi>Verſes</hi> in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> it naturally led me into that weighty Controverſy about the <hi>Authority of the Points in the Hebrew Text,</hi> which occaſion'd it's growth into a larger bulk than was fit for a Preface; whereupon I was feign to ſlip it off, and ſeparate it from that Root, and ſo it grew up into a diſtinct Diſcourſe by it ſelf; wherein the Reader will meet with ſomething not to be found elſe where (for I would not trouble the World with old matters new vamp't up.)</p>
            <p>When this Diſcourſe was firſt conceived and brought forth; (which was ſome Years ago) as they ſay the Eagle tries her young ones by expoſing 'em to the light of the Sun, ſo, being deſirous that the Truth and Soundneſs of my Notion might be thorowly tried, I ſent it to ſome learned Perſons for their Opinion about it. I found that they had a different appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the Controverſy from mine, and
<pb facs="tcp:39375:5"/> made ſome ſlight Objections againſt my judgment of it: but none of 'em did at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any Anſwer to any of my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or endeavour in the leaſt to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the foundation of my Building, <hi>viz. The Connection between the Verſes, Accents and Vowels;</hi> which confirmed me in my Opinion, that it is built upon good Grounds, becauſe the moſt learned Perſons that have peruſed it, have ſo little to object againſt it. The moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Objection made by a very learned, judicious Divine was (not ſo much againſt my Opinion it ſelf, as) that it is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proved that <hi>all</hi> the Hebrew <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents</hi> are, and muſt be coetaneous with the <hi>Verſes</hi> and <hi>Language.</hi> I grant that my Argument does not directly prove that <hi>All</hi> the <hi>Accents</hi> are Coevous with the <hi>Vowels,</hi> but only <hi>Athnach</hi> and <hi>Silluk:</hi> But then if it be conſider'd, that they all have a dependance one upon another, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Duces</hi> and <hi>Subditi,</hi> or <hi>Miniſtri,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Reges;</hi> then the proving of ſome of 'em to be coetaneous with the Vowels
<pb facs="tcp:39375:5"/> and Verſes, bids fair for the proof of 'em all.</p>
            <p>The Uſefulneſs of the <hi>Accents,</hi> and their intimate connection with, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance one upon another, is very fully ſhewed of late by Mr. <hi>Walter Croſs</hi> in his <hi>Taghmical Art</hi> (as he calls it; tho' I ſhould think, according to the Rules and Analogy of Grammar, it ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be called, the <hi>Tangnamical Art,</hi> (as from <hi>Talmud, Talmudical:</hi>) for the Noun Subſtantive, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>tangnam,</hi> an <hi>Accent,</hi>) which very well deſerves the diligent Study of all thoſe that deſire to be exact in the <hi>Hebrew Tongue,</hi> and conſequently in the underſtanding of the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament: only one great Diſaſter has befallen it, (which probably might come to paſs by his Illneſs, or Death) that it is very falſe Printed.</p>
            <p>It has bin ſuggeſted to me by ſome learned Men that have ſeen thoſe Papers, That being fit only for the View of the Learned, (and, alas! not for all of them neither) it ſhould have bin dreſs'd up and
<pb facs="tcp:39375:6"/> ſent abroad in a learned Habit; but fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling only accidentally upon that Queſtion, I ſpun out my thoughts upon it by degrees, after the ſame rate that I had begun it, till I had finiſht my Web, and don't think it now worth while to put it into a new dreſs, but e'en let it go as it is, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it ſelf to the Candid Reader as well as it can.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third Diſcourſe</hi> treats of a nice and curious Point <hi>(The Teſtimony of the Spirit,)</hi> which is not ſo much a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Speculation</hi> as <hi>Experience:</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which I know nothing that has bin publiſht of late about it, diſtinctly by it ſelf; and therefore perhaps it may find the better Acceptance with the Reader, eſpecially if he be one that has his <hi>Senſes exerciſed</hi> about ſuch things.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sa. Clark.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:39375:6"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>§ <hi>1.</hi> THE Unſearchableneſs of God's Works.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>2.</hi> Eſpecially of the Work of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon the Souls of men. § <hi>3.</hi> And more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as to the Inſpiration of the Holy Scriptures.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>4. La Mothe's</hi> Account of it.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>5.</hi> The Nature of it open'd in ſeveral Propoſitions.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Prop. <hi>The Holy Scriptures contain mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſeveral ſorts.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>§ <hi>6. 2.</hi> Prop. <hi>All Scripture, of what ſort ſoever, is by Inſpiration from God.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>§ <hi>7.</hi> Proved by Parts.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Concerning the Scriptures of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that they are divinely inſpired, is proved,
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>1.</hi> By the Teſtimonies of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter, 2 Tim. 3.16. 2 Pet. 1.21.</hi> which are open'd.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ <hi>8. 2.</hi> By a diſtinct conſideration of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Books. <hi>(1.)</hi> Of <hi>Moſes.</hi> § <hi>9. (2.)</hi> Of the Hiſtorical Books. § <hi>10. (3.)</hi> Of <hi>Job,</hi> § <hi>11. (4.)</hi> Of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> and <hi>Prophets.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>§ <hi>12. 3.</hi> By many Paſſages, which muſt be the immediate dictates of the Holy Spirit.</item>
                     <item>§ <hi>13. 2.</hi> The Scriptures of the New Teſtament proved to be God-inſpir'd by ſeveral Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>§ <hi>14. 3.</hi> Prop. <hi>The Perſons inſpired had the uſe of their Reaſon and Underſtanding.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§ <hi>15. 4.</hi> Prop. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt made uſe of the Natural Abilities of the Perſons inſpired.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>§ <hi>16. 5.</hi> Prop. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt accommodated his Inſpiration to the particular Genius of every Writer.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:39375:7"/>
               <item>§ <hi>17. 6.</hi> Prop. <hi>This Inſpiration included many things in it.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>— <hi>1.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt ſtirr'd 'em up to write.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>§ <hi>18.—2.</hi> He ſet 'em their Task.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>19.—3.</hi> He inlighten'd their minds, and gave 'em a diſtinct underſtanding of what was to be deliver'd by 'em. § <hi>20.</hi> Show'd <hi>(1.)</hi> In the Hiſtorical Parts. § <hi>21. (2.)</hi> In the Prophetical. § <hi>22. (3.)</hi> In the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Apoſtles. § <hi>23.</hi> The ſeveral ſteps by which knowledge was communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to them. § <hi>24.</hi> But to <hi>Paul</hi> it was all at once: Several peculiar Privileges belonging to him.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>25.—4.</hi> He ſtrengthned their Memories.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>26.—5.</hi> He directed 'em what Matters of Fact to inſert.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>27.—6.</hi> He call'd forth thoſe images of things which were laid up in their minds.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>28.—7.</hi> He ſuggeſted to 'em immediately what was matter of pure Revelation.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>29.—8.</hi> He had a general Inſtruction over the whole, to make it a compleat Rule both of Faith and Life.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>30. 7th, and Laſt</hi> Prop. <hi>The whole Scripture both in reſpect of Matter and Words, is of Divine Inſpiration.</hi> § <hi>31.</hi> Proved by ſeveral Paſſages of Scripture. § <hi>32.</hi> And by Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Learned Men.</item>
               <item>§ <hi>33.</hi> The Sum of the whole, ſhowing the diſtinct Share both of the Holy Ghoſt and Pen-men of the Scriptures.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:39375:7"/>
            <head>There is extant alſo of the ſame Author,</head>
            <p>ANnotations on the Bible; with Parallel Scriptures (much more largely than in any other Edition) and a Concordance. Sold by <hi>Jon. Robinſon</hi> and <hi>Brab. Aylmer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Survey of the Bible: Or, An Analytical Account of the Bible, by Chapter and Verſe: by way of Supplement to the Annotations. 4<hi>to.</hi> Printed for <hi>Jon. Robinſon.</hi> Price 8 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Brief Concordance of the moſt uſual and uſeful Places: ſo that one ſhall ſeldom have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to look into a large Concordance, as has been found by Experience. In large Twelves. Sold by <hi>J. Robinſon.</hi> Price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Abridgment of the Hiſtorical Parts of the Scripture. In Twelves. Printed for <hi>J. Robinſon.</hi> Price 1<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of Scandal: Wherein theſe weighty Queſtions are fully diſcuſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether things Indifferent become Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, when commanded by Authority? <hi>Neg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether things Scandalous being enjoined, may lawfully be done? <hi>Neg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. How far forth we are bound in Conſcience to obey Humane Laws? With others. Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with</p>
            <p>An Exercitation on <hi>Matth.</hi> XV. 1.-9. Sold by <hi>T. Parkhurſt.</hi> Price 9 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Ordination Sermon on <hi>Acts</hi> XIII. 2, 3. Printed for <hi>J. Lawrence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Scripture-Juſtification. Printed for <hi>T. Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:39375:8"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Exercitation.</head>
               <p>PAge 5. l. 15. for <hi>Megittoth,</hi> read <hi>Megilloth.</hi> p. 6. l. 14 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the Break at [I find], and l. 15, 16. r. Chapters both between. p. 14. l. 16. for 13. r. 3. p. 40. l. 12. for <hi>his,</hi> r. <hi>this.</hi> p. 43. l. laſt, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> words at the bottom of the page ſhould have been inſerted between the Crotchets in the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> line of the Margin, and read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Teſtimony.</head>
               <p>Page 8. l. 2. before <hi>Nil,</hi> add, <hi>This is.</hi> p. 19. l. 32. for <hi>Whetſtone,</hi> r. <hi>White ſtone.</hi> p. 23. l. 23. for <hi>great</hi> r. <hi>other.</hi> p. 27. l. 29. for <hi>where,</hi> r. <hi>when.</hi> p. 29. l. 7. for <hi>wrapt,</hi> r. <hi>rapt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there be any other Faults, the Reader is deſired to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe 'em, for the Author did not ſee all the Sheets.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39375:8"/>
            <head>An Exercitation, Diſquiſition, or Enquiry into the Nature and Extent of the Inſpiration of the Holy Scriptures.</head>
            <p n="1">§. 1. THE Works of God in general, are very unſearchable by any humane Underſtanding. <hi>Great things doth he which we cannot comprehend,</hi> ſaith <hi>Elihu,</hi> Job 37.—5, <hi>nor find out,</hi> v. 23. So that, <hi>No man can know the work that God doth from the beginning to the end;</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> aſſures us, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.—11. Particularly,</p>
            <p>Concerning the Works of Providence, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> pronounces of 'em, that <hi>they are a great deep,</hi> Pſal. 36.6. and again, 77.19. <hi>Thy way is in the ſea, and thy path in great waters, and thy footſteps are not known.</hi> This moved <hi>Zophar</hi> to put the queſtion to <hi>Job, c.</hi> 11. 7, 8. <hi>Canst thou by ſearching find out God? Canſt thou find out the Almighty to perfection? It is high as heaven, What canſt thou do? deeper than hell, what canſt thou know?</hi> The conſideration whereof drew that <hi>Exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>Admiration</hi> from the great Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>! <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God! How unſearchable are his judgments!
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39375:9"/> and his ways paſt finding out,</hi> Rom. 11.36.</p>
            <p n="2">§. 2. But eſpecially the <hi>Work of the Spirit</hi> in and upon the Souls of Men, is very myſterious, and incomprehenſible, as to the finer ſtrokes of it. Our Saviour Chriſt compares it to the <hi>Wind,</hi> Joh. 3.8. <hi>The Wind blows where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof, but canſt not tell whence it comes, and whither it goes. So is every one that is born of the Spirit.</hi> As the <hi>Effects</hi> of the Wind are ſenſible and diſcernible enough, but the Manner is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable; ſo the <hi>effects</hi> of the Work of the Spirit are evident enough, but the <hi>Manner</hi> is very myſterious and incomprehenſible.</p>
            <p n="3">§. 3. This may be applied (among other things) to the <hi>Inſpiration</hi> of the Spirit in the <hi>holy Men of God,</hi> the Penmen of Scripture. That it is ſo, that they were Divinely inſpir'd, we have demonſtrative proof and evidence ſufficient; but the <hi>Manner</hi> of it is not obvious, nor eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; yet it is <hi>ſought out of all them that have pleaſure therein;</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>c.</hi> 111. 2. This therefore I ſhall endeavour to open and explain <hi>pro modulo meo,</hi> ſo far forth as I can attain unto; and to adjuſt the bounds, and fix the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, as near as I can, between the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and the <hi>holy Men of God;</hi> and ſhew the <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>ſhare</hi> of each in this performance; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is none that I have met with in the narrow compaſs of my Reading, that has hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it to my ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein I implore the Aſſiſtance of that Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the Inditer of the Holy Scriptures, that I may ſteer an even courſe without turning aſide to the right hand or to the left, by attributing either too much or too little to either of 'em, but may render to God the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39375:9"/> things that are God's, and to Man the things that are Man's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">§. 4. There is indeed a late Author <hi>(La Mothe)</hi> who has written a Diſcourſe upon this Subject, Intitled, <hi>[The Inſpiration of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſerted and explain'd.]</hi> I ſhall firſt. give an account of his Explication, and then offer my own ſenſe and thoughts to conſideration. His Judgment in the caſe he expreſſes thus; <hi>That we may have a diſtinct</hi> Idea <hi>of the Inſpiration of the Holy Writings, 'tis requiſite to diſtinguiſh the things which they contain; which I ſhall do into three Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. In the firſt I ſhall put the Revelations. The ſecond is for thoſe things which the Apoſtles learnt by the natural aſſiſtances of their Hearing and Sight. In the third you ſhall ſee the Progreſs which they made by reaſoning upon the Truths of the two firſt Orders.— So that you ſee the Apostles wrote things which they knew by Revelation, by Senſe, or by Reaſoning.</hi> P. 103.</p>
            <p>In reference to the <hi>Revelations</hi> which the Apoſtles had, he ſaith, <hi>The Holy Ghost acts two ways in relation to the Truths which he has revealed by the Apostles. First he ſuggested thoſe Truths which he imprinted in their Souls by ſome of thoſe ways which I have ſet down, wherein the Apostles were in a paſſive diſpoſition; like a piece of Cloth that receives the Colours. 'Tis in this manner that they were inſtructed; but when they ſet themſelves to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct others, and communicate in writing what the Holy Ghost had taught 'em, he acted after another manner: he puſht 'em forward to write: he strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and refreſht their Memories; and ſo directed their Pens that they wrote nothing which was not to the purpoſe, and according to the most exact Rules of Truth. There was then in the written Revelations
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39375:10"/> which they have left us, two ſorts of Inſpiration; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of Suggeſtion, and Inſpiration of Direction.</hi> P. 108. <hi>He ſuggeſted to 'em thoſe things that they knew not; but as for thoſe things which they knew they had need only of his Direction to render 'em in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible in their Writings.</hi> P. 109. And preſently after he ſpeaks to this purpoſe, <q rend="margQuotes">That ſome things they knew by their Education: others by common Converſation. Concerning theſe a new Suggeſtion was abſolutely needleſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Miracles are not to be multiplied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out neceſſity. Therefore he did not whiſper into the Ears of the Apoſtles what they knew before. He was not obliged to begin but where Nature had ended. It was enough that he ſpake when ſhe became ſilent.</q> 
               <hi>Let us not imagine that he was only a Spectator of the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Nature; He brought her to Perfection, and hindred her from going aſtray.</hi> P. 111. <hi>The ſhare which we believe the Holy Ghoſt had in the writing of thoſe things</hi> (which they knew before) <hi>is</hi> 1. <hi>That he was the</hi> Primum Mobile <hi>of the Compoſition; 'twas he that ſet the Apoſtles at work, whether it were in furniſhing 'em with Occaſions and Subjects to write upon; or whether it were by ſecretly stirring 'em up to write, I may ſay, He put the Pen in their Hands.</hi> 2. <hi>He preſided in the Choice of the Matter which was to be put into the work, not ſuffering the Apostles to write any thing but what was true, and to the purpoſe. This is an Inſpiration of Direction; nor does there need any more to be ſaid, as to the Truths which they had heard and ſeen.</hi> P. 112. <hi>He let's 'em alone when they go right, and when they are about to miſcarry, he brings 'em back again.</hi> P. 121.</p>
            <p>For their own <hi>Reaſonings, 'Tis known,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to be the uſual custom of the Apostles, to accompany
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39375:10"/> the Truths which the Spirit ſuggeſted to 'em with certain Reflections.</hi> e.g. <hi>St.</hi> Peter <hi>joining the Viſion of the Sheet, to the Viſion that was ſeen by</hi> Cornelius, <hi>Of a truth,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>now I perceive that God is no reſpecter of perſons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>St.</hi> Paul, <hi>after he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared what the Spirit had ſaid in expreſs terms touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as would depart from the Faith, makes a ſhort Diſcourſe upon it,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1.— <hi>When thus they reaſon'd upon the Oracles, the Apoſtles had no need of being inſpir'd; to take the word in a ſenſe of Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. Their Reaſon fortified and guided by the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe Inſtruments they were, was ſufficient for 'em to find out in the revealed Propoſitions the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that were included in 'em. Natural Logick would have ſerved the Turn: Here we have no recourſe to the Holy Ghoſt, but to warrant the Infallibility of the Reflection of the Apoſtles.</hi> P. 113, 114.</p>
            <p>This is the ſubſtance of the whole of his Judgment herein. But this account ſeems to me very lame and defective, and alſo Derogatory to the Majeſty and Authority of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; and therefore I have beſtow'd ſome thoughts upon it for my own ſatisfaction; which I have muſter'd up together, and drawn forth in theſe enſuing Propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="5">§. 5. <hi>Prop. I. The Holy Scriptures contain Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſeveral ſorts.</hi> The Subject Matter of the Holy Scriptures is various, and of divers ſorts; Some Parts of the Scripture are <hi>Hiſtorical,</hi> recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding what has bin done in former times: Some are <hi>Prophetical,</hi> foretelling what ſhall be done hereafter: Some <hi>Doctrinal,</hi> teaching what we muſt Believe; and ſome <hi>Practical,</hi> acquainting us with our Duty, which we muſt do, or leave undone. And theſe are interwoven with <hi>Precepts, Prohibitions, Promiſes, Threatnings, Prayers, Soliloquies,</hi> and the like.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:39375:11"/>
            <p>It is neceſſary that we diſtinguiſh theſe well the one from the other, becauſe they require ſeveral ſorts of Inſpiration, as will appear in what follows.</p>
            <p n="6">§ 6. <hi>Prop.</hi> II. <hi>It is the Property and Prerogative of all Scripture, of what ſort ſoever, to be by Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God.</hi> This not being my main buſineſs, but only in order to it, as I paſs along, I ſhall not go far for evidence, but content my ſelf with ſuch Proofs as are ready at hand, and offer themſelves willingly to my thoughts.</p>
            <p n="7">§ 7. This Propoſition I ſhall prove particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and by Parts, in reference to the Scriptures both of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament:</hi> Wherein it is not ſo much my purpoſe to <hi>convince</hi> or confute Antiſcripturiſts (this has been done abundantly and unanſwerably by many more able and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pens) as to <hi>confirm</hi> honeſt, humble Souls, that are willing to be ſatisfied by ſuch plain, intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Arguments as are contained in, and taken out of the Bowels of the Scripture it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Scriptures of the Old Teſtament are by Inſpiration of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I ſhall prove,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the Teſtimony of the two great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> It is expreſly affirmed by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>All Scripture</hi> (not only ſome parts of ſuch and ſuch Books, but the whole Scripture, and whole of Scripture: Whatſoever comes under the name of Scripture, without any diſtinction or difference; by whomſoever written is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God-inſpired.</hi> Not <hi>[All Scripture that is God-inſpired]</hi> (as the <hi>Polonian</hi>-Merchants would have it) as if there were ſome that were not ſo: for the Verb Subſtantive muſt needs be underſtood
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39375:11"/> between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and not between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe the Conjunction comes between, which renders <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be the ſecond Epithet of) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the firſt. Here are two things affirmed concerning the Scripture (as <hi>Eſtius</hi> obſerves,) (1.) Its <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> that it is from God. (2.) Its <hi>Utility,</hi> that it is profitable for the Ends and Purpoſes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This then muſt needs include at leaſt all the Scriptures of the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> alſo affirms the ſame, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>For the prophecy came not in old time</hi> (or rather <hi>at any time,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>by the will of man: but holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Where obſerve (1.) The <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> he ſpeaks of; with the <hi>Title</hi> whereby he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it, <hi>Prophecy:</hi> which is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>ſtrictly,</hi> for the Foretelling of things to come; or the Writings only of the Prophets; but <hi>largely,</hi> for any <hi>Revelation</hi> or <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of the Will of God to the Penmen of Scripture. This appears by <hi>v.</hi> 19. where he ſaith, <hi>We have a more ſure word of Prophecy</hi> (that is, of the Revelation of the Will of God, <hi>viz.</hi> in Scripture; in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinction to the Revelation of God's Will in that Voice that came from Heaven to Chriſt at his Transfiguration) —<hi>whereto you do well to give heed.</hi> This is a duty that belongs to the whole Scripture of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> as well as to the <hi>Prophetical</hi> parts, and therefore includes the whole. Hence all the <hi>Penmen</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> are called <hi>Prophets, Eph.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.26. And therefore the word <hi>[Prophecy]</hi> here, muſt include the whole. Of this <hi>Voice</hi> he ſhews the <hi>Original:</hi> and that both <hi>Negatively; It came not by the Will of man.</hi> It was not the <hi>Conception,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39375:12"/> Compoſure,</hi> Indictment or Product of mens own Brains, nor the Suggeſtion of their own Spirits; They were not the <hi>firſt Movers</hi> in this Work: But, <hi>Poſitively, holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Where obſerve (1.) The <hi>primum mobile,</hi> or firſt Mover, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> (2.) The <hi>Inſtrumental Cauſe,</hi> or Inſtruments he made uſe of, <hi>holy men of God.</hi> Such were all the Penmen of the ſeveral Books of the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</hi> (3.) <hi>What befel 'em:</hi> How it fared with 'em in this Work, when they wrote theſe Books; <hi>they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. As the <hi>Writings</hi> of the Scriptures were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (according to <hi>Paul</hi>) ſo the <hi>Writers</hi> were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (according to <hi>Peter</hi> here) <hi>acted and moved by the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> under his immediate Conduct and impulſe. As the Spirit <hi>came upon the Apoſtles on the day of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt, as a ruſhing, mighty wind,</hi> Act. 2.2. (the ſame word is uſed there, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſo he ruſhed in a powerful manner upon theſe holy men of God, the Penmen of the holy Scriptures. (4.) <hi>When,</hi> or upon what Occaſion it was thus with 'em: It was in reference to what <hi>they ſpake:</hi> which includes their <hi>Writing</hi> alſo: For the Prophets did deliver all their Propheſies to the People by word of mouth firſt, and then wrote 'em down afterwards, as appears by ſome Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in <hi>Jeremy.</hi> But for ſome other parts of Scripture they were only written: yet this <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> or what was ſo written, was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us in the place beforementioned. Beſides, The Subject that <hi>Peter</hi> is here treating of is the whole Scripture; as appears by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, <hi>v.</hi> 19. and I proved before. And ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed concerning the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39375:12"/> 
               <hi>Acts</hi> 2.31. <hi>David ſpake of the Reſurrection of Chriſt,</hi> (viz. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.10.) <hi>i. e.</hi> wrote. So <hi>Acts</hi> 3.24. <hi>All the Prophets from Samuel, and thoſe that follow after, as many as have ſpoken, have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe foretold of theſe days,</hi> Rom. 3.19. <hi>Whatſoever the law (i. e.</hi> the whole Scripture of the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> as appears by the foregoing words) <hi>ſaith, it ſaith to them that are under the law.</hi> Hence the Scriptures in general are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Oracles of God,</hi> Rom. 3.2.</p>
            <p n="8">§ 8. 2. That the Scriptures of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> are by Divine Inſpiration, I prove by a diſtinct view and conſideration of the ſeveral Books of the <hi>Old Teſtament;</hi> whereby it will appear that there is an evident character and ſtamp of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity imprinted upon 'em.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>For the Books of Moſes:</hi> They contain an account of many things before his own Time, which he muſt have either by <hi>Revelation, Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>Writings</hi> and Records.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Some things muſt of neceſſity be by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation:</hi> As, What God ſaid to <hi>Cain,</hi> Gen. 4.6, 7, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for it's very unlikely that <hi>Cain</hi> himſelf would tell it to any. So <hi>Lamech</hi>'s Speech to his Wives, <hi>v.</hi> 23, 24. God's purpoſe to deſtroy the Old World by the Flood, <hi>ch.</hi> 6. 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God's accepting of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Sacrifice, <hi>ch.</hi> 8. 21. — <hi>he ſaid in his heart.</hi> What God ſaid concerning the building of <hi>Babel,</hi> ch. 11. 6, 7. The cauſe of the Plague on <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Houſe, <hi>ch.</hi> 12. 17. God's dealing with <hi>Abimelech</hi> concerning <hi>Sarah, ch.</hi> 20. 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Paſſages between <hi>Abimelech</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> concerning his Wife, <hi>ch.</hi> 26. 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What God ſaid to <hi>Laban</hi> in a Dream, <hi>ch.</hi> 31. 24. <hi>Rachel</hi>'s ſitting upon the Images, <hi>v.</hi> 34. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren againſt him, <hi>ch.</hi> 37.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39375:13"/> 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The reaſon why <hi>Er</hi> and <hi>Onan</hi> were ſlain, <hi>ch.</hi> 38. 7 — 10. <hi>Judah</hi>'s lying with <hi>Tamar,</hi> v. 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and many ſuch Paſſages.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) For <hi>Tradition</hi> and <hi>Writing,</hi> It's very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely that many things recorded by <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould either be conveigh'd by <hi>Tradition,</hi> or committed to <hi>Writing:</hi> As, The Agreement between <hi>Abram</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> to ſay, <hi>She was his ſiſter,</hi> Gen. 12.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What paſs'd between <hi>Abram</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> v. 18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What paſs'd between <hi>Abram</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> c. 13. 8, <hi>&amp;c. Sarah</hi>'s giving her Maid to <hi>Abram,</hi> c. 16. 2, 3. What <hi>Rebecca</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> c. 27. 46. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>'s device about the Sheep, <hi>c.</hi> 30. 37, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, and multitudes of ſuch private, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, perſonal Paſſages, are not proper matter either for <hi>Tradition,</hi> or a <hi>Hiſtory:</hi> and therefore they muſt be made known to <hi>Moſes</hi> by <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some things alſo which were done in his Time, and recorded by him, yet were <hi>foreign Affairs:</hi> Such wherein he had no perſonal concernment, and therefore could not be known by him but by <hi>Revelation:</hi> as the Paſſages between <hi>Balack</hi> and <hi>Balaam;</hi> and the Angel's ſtanding in the way to ſlay <hi>Balaam,</hi> Num. 22, <hi>&amp;</hi> 23, <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.</p>
            <p n="9">§ 9. <hi>Secondly,</hi> For the <hi>Hiſtorical Books,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Matters of Fact,</hi> there are many things there alſo which could not be known but by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate <hi>Revelation:</hi> As, God's being angry with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and what he ſaid thereupon; <hi>Judg.</hi> 2.20— 23. What <hi>Gaal</hi> ſaid privately to the men of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem,</hi> c. 9. 28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Paſſages between <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> and his <hi>Mother,</hi> c. 17. 2-5. What the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> ſaid one to another, <hi>c.</hi> 18. 14. The Paſſages between the <hi>Levite</hi> and his Father-in-law, <hi>c.</hi> 19. 5-10. and thoſe Paſſages, <hi>v.</hi> 16-26. All the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39375:13"/> 
               <hi>Book of Ruth.</hi> The carriage of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> about the Ark, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.6. How ſhould it be known what the Servants of the King of <hi>Syria</hi> ſaid to him, but by <hi>Revelation?</hi> 1 King. 20.23-25. All the beginning of the Story of <hi>Naaman</hi> (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.) probably was by <hi>Revelation</hi> only. What is ſpoken of God, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 14.26, 27.</p>
            <p>It's evident that theſe things, or moſt of 'em, could be known no otherwiſe than by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Inſpiration: And if ſome be by Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then all are; for Chriſt makes no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence when he bids us <hi>ſearch the Scriptures:</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith expreſly, <hi>That all Scripture is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="10">§ 10. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> For the <hi>Book of Job,</hi> it may be lookt upon as an Hiſtorical Book, though the Hiſtory doth contain Doctrinal matter of divers ſorts, yet it's all <hi>Matter of fact;</hi> being a Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of what was ſpoken by one and another: wherein, though <hi>Job</hi>'s Friends were in the wrong as to their particular Application of what they ſaid to <hi>Job,</hi> yet it is obſerved, That they were ſo guided (by the Spirit of God, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) that there's no one Sentence conſider'd ſingly by it ſelf, that is contrary to other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Beſides, This is one of the Books we have received from the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were God's Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees and Depoſitaries for the ſafe cuſtody of the <hi>Oracles</hi> of God; <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. and they were never taxed for unfaithfulneſs in this truſt, either by Chriſt or the Apoſtles: And further, the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity thereof is fully confirmed by that Paſſage of St. <hi>James,</hi> c. 5. 11. and by thoſe other Paſſages quoted in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> out of it.</p>
            <p n="11">§ 11. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That the <hi>Pſalms</hi> were indicted by the Spirit of God appears by theſe places;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39375:14"/> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.2. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.36. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7. And then, many of 'em are <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical,</hi> of Chriſt, his Kingdom, Sufferings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and of the Calling of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Writings of the Prophets are moſt evidently of <hi>Divine Inſpiration;</hi> for they are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally nothing but a <hi>Rehearſal</hi> or <hi>Tranſcript</hi> of what God ſpake <hi>To</hi> and <hi>By</hi> 'em; as appears by the ſeveral particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſay</hi> is nothing but a Collection of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, and ſo, all the very Words of God: on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a part of <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s Hiſtory, <hi>ch.</hi> 36-39.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> are moſtly the ſame too; enterwoven with ſome Hiſtorical Paſſages of the Affairs of the Church in thoſe times, and ſome of their own perſonal Concerns: Wherein, tho ſome things were the product of their own Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits (as thoſe paſſionate Expreſſions, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet the recording of 'em in Scripture was by the ſpecial direction of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> is a good part of it <hi>Prophetical,</hi> and therefore muſt be of divine Original.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſea</hi> contains nothing but the Words of God; except the account of his Obedience to God's Command, <hi>c.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joel</hi> is all the Words of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amos</hi> the ſame; except a Narrative of ſome Viſions, <hi>c.</hi> 7. 8. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obadiah,</hi> only the Words of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jonah</hi> Hiſtorical.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Micah,</hi> the Words of God moſtly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nahum</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Habakkuk</hi> a kind of <hi>Dialogue</hi> between God and the Prophet, <hi>c.</hi> 1, <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. and a <hi>Prayer,</hi> c. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zephaniah,</hi> all of it the Words of God.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:39375:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Haggai</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zechariah</hi> conſiſts moſt of Viſions concerning the State of the Church in thoſe days. See the Argument to it in my Annotations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Malachi,</hi> all of it the Words of God.</p>
            <p>So that it is moſt apparent that all this part of Scripture is of divine Inſpiration; yea that the very words were dictated to 'em by the Spirit of God, though accommodated to the particular <hi>genius</hi> of every one; as will be ſeen <hi>Prop.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="12">§ 12. 3. How many things are there in the Scriptures of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> (as well as the <hi>New</hi>) which tranſcend all humane Abilities, and not to be match'd in any humane Writings, and are peculiar to God alone? Never could enter into the heart of man any thing like that <hi>Dialogue</hi> between God the Father, and God the Son, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.1-12. Never did or could any man declare the ſincerity of the heart, whenas the Actions might ſeem to argue the contrary, as in <hi>Aſa,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13. with 16.10, 12. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, nor could any ſpeak in the name of God, as the Scripture frequently doth: <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> Never did any man pretend to make ſuch Promiſes and Threatnings of Spiritual and Eternal things, as the Scripture doth. Where are ſuch lofty ſtrains to be found in any humane Authors, as that <hi>Deſcription</hi> of the Entertainment of the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> by his Dead Confederates? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.21-32. or that Elegant <hi>Proſopopeia</hi> of the Inanimate Creatures, and the dead at the deſtruction of <hi>Babylon;</hi> and for the King of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi>'s Entertainment in the Grave, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.9-20. as alſo of God's Judgments upon the <hi>Jews</hi> for their treacherous dealing with the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> Iſa. 24.17-23. Conſider alſo the lofty ſtrain of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39375:15"/> thoſe Paſſages and Prophecies which are ſpoken by the Prophets in the name of God; as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24. and <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Addreſs to God thereupon, <hi>c.</hi> 25. and 26. So, no man could ever have certainly told that the reaſon why the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were viſited with ſuch ſickneſſes and weakneſſes, was for their eating and drinking unworthily at the Lord's Table, if it had not been immediately dictated to him by the Holy Ghoſt. Theſe things and many ſuch like could not have their Riſe from any Man's brain, but muſt come <hi>aliunde,</hi> yea <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>from above;</hi> muſt be put into 'em by the immediate Dictate of the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p n="13">§. 13. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the Scriptures of the New Teſtament are equal ſharers with thoſe of the Old Teſtament in this Priviledg and Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God-inſpired.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Writings of the New Teſtament are comprehended in the word <hi>[Scripture]</hi> and call'd by that name, as well as the Writings of the Old Teſtament. <hi>Peter</hi> gives this Title to <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.— <hi>As alſo in all his Epiſtles, in which there are ſome things hard to be underſtood, which they that are unlearned and unſtable wreſt, as they do the other Scriptures to their own deſtruction;</hi> imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles ſtand upon the ſame ground, and have as good a title and claim to the word <hi>[Scripture]</hi> as any other Writings what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Scriptures of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> are the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our Faith, as well as the Scriptures of the <hi>Prophets, Eph.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Paul</hi> was endued with Divine Wiſdom in what he wrote, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. and expreſly affirms of himſelf, that what he ſpake and wrote was,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39375:15"/> 
               <hi>The Word of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7-40. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.37. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Goſpel-diſpenſation being much more glorious in many reſpects than that of the Law, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7-11.) and the Apoſtles being the chief Officers in the New Teſtament, they muſt at leaſt have an equal aſſiſtance with the higheſt under the Law. Nay rather, as he that is leaſt in the Kingdom of God is greater than he that was greater than all the Prophets, ſo the Divine Abilities of the Apoſtles muſt much more excel thoſe of the Prophets.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Otherwiſe all the Promiſes and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings delivered by the Apoſtles would be of no force nor efficacy, nor could have any influence upon the Conſcience; the contrary whereto is found by daily experience; and therefore their Writings muſt be immediate dictates of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt as well as thoſe delivered by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and which Chriſt ſpake with his own mouth.</p>
            <p>And if theſe <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Threatnings</hi> were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd by the Inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, then alſo what goes <hi>before,</hi> and what follows <hi>after;</hi> for they are ſo nearly linkt together, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven one with another that they muſt proceed from the ſame Spirit. For, can any one think that the Holy Ghoſt aſſiſted the Apoſtles by <hi>Suggeſtion</hi> in one Verſe and paſſage, and only by <hi>Direction, (i. e.</hi> by watching over 'em that they ſhould not err) in the next? Look over all thoſe <hi>precious Promiſes</hi> wherewith the Apoſtolical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings are beſpangled, as the Sky with Stars, (which I have recited in the <hi>Table of the Promiſes</hi> at the end of my <hi>Annotations on the Bible</hi>) and judg whether they could proceed from any but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39375:16"/> one immediately acted and aſſiſted by the Holy Ghoſt in the writing of 'em. And then further conſider 'em with the <hi>Antecedents</hi> and <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents,</hi> and the cloſe, intimate Union between 'em, and then judge whether they don't evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently diſcover the ſame kind of Aſſiſtance in the whole. I'le inſtance but in one, <hi>viz.</hi> that Promiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. <hi>For ſin ſhall not have domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over you.</hi> Obſerve how the Apoſtle brings it in, in the ſame thread, or tenor of diſcourſe with what goes before: and therefore they muſt be all of the ſame ſtamp; and if the <hi>Promiſes</hi> (and ſo for the <hi>Threatnings</hi>) be the immediate Dictates of the Spirit, ſo muſt the reſt alſo.</p>
            <p>It is not with the Writings of the Apoſtles as with a piece of Embroider'd work, which is firſt wrought in the Loom by one hand, and then Embroider'd by another; but like a piece of rich Silk inwrought with Flowers of Gold and Silver, all of a piece; wrought by the ſame hand, all at the ſame time, yet one part is rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than another: So it is with theſe compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, though one part be richer than another, yet all is the work of the ſame hand.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Yet we may obſerve ſome difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Writings of the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> in theſe three reſpects eſpecially. (1) The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> deliver'd all in the Name of the Lord: <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord:</hi> whereas the Apoſtles wrote in their own Names: ſo moſt of the Epiſtles begin, and have the Name of the Penman ſet in the Front. (2) The Books of the <hi>Prophets</hi> are but a <hi>Collection,</hi> or aggregate Body of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Prophecies or Viſions added one to another: whereas the Writings of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> are carried on in a continued tenor of Diſcourſe, with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39375:16"/> any ſuch interruptions, and breaking off the thread of the Matter, as in the Prophets. (3.) The <hi>Prophets</hi> had not a conſtant, uninterrupted influx of the Spirit, but he fell upon 'em at certain Times and Seaſons, according to his own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; therefore you have the ſeveral Prophecies of the ſame Prophet bearing date at ſeveral times: and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was made dumb, in ſome reſpect, till a certain ſeaſon, <hi>c.</hi> 3. 26, 27. and 24. 27. <hi>See my Annotations there.</hi> So when the Captains of the Forces and <hi>Johanan</hi> came to <hi>Jeremy</hi> for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from him (<hi>Jer.</hi> 42.1-3.) it is ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 7. that <hi>after ten days came the Word of the Lord to Jeremiah:</hi> Whereas the Apoſtles ſeem to have had a conſtant aſſiſtance of the Spirit upon all occaſions; ſo that whereſoever they came, they were ready to preach the Word of God to the People of thoſe places. And therefore in this reſpect the Apoſtles had much the pre-eminence and advantage of the Prophets, as was hinted juſt now, <hi>n.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>So then the whole Bulk and Body of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture contain'd in the Writings of the Old and New Teſtament is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God-inſpired;</hi> which is the <hi>ſecond Propoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">§. 14. Prop. III. <hi>This Inſpiration did not deprive the Perſons inſpired, of their Reaſon and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Thus indeed it befel thoſe by whom the Devil deliver'd his Oracles: for the Evil Spirit that poſſeſt 'em, uſed to ſwell and blow up their Bodies, eſpecially their Breaſts and Bellies, like a Bladder or Bottle, (as it is recorded of the <hi>Pythian</hi> Propheteſs, or Witch rather) and to caſt 'em into a kind of Frenzy, and then deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd his Oracles by 'em with a hoarſe or hollow Voice, as if they ſpake out of their <hi>Bellies</hi> (thence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39375:17"/> call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the <hi>Greeks</hi>) or out of a <hi>Bottle,</hi> whence they had their Name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Hebrew. But it was not ſo with thoſe that were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: they were not <hi>mente capti,</hi> and ſo uſed only as Pipes to convey ſuch and ſuch things thorow 'em, to which they contributed nothing at all, except the <hi>Writing,</hi> but were meerly <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive. Bede</hi> (on 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.) mentions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes ſome in his time that maintain'd this fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh fancy. Neither were they uſed as meer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuenſes</hi> to write what the Holy Ghoſt dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted word for word to 'em, without the uſe of their own Judgment: but the Holy Ghoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd 'em as <hi>reaſonable Perſons,</hi> endu'd with abilities of Underſtanding, Judgment, and the like. Their Faculties were not <hi>laid aſide,</hi> nor <hi>laid aſleep</hi> (as <hi>Adam</hi>'s was when he loſt his Rib.) They did not <hi>put off</hi> Man when they <hi>put on</hi> God: But,</p>
            <p n="15">§. 15. Prop. IV. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt made uſe of the Natural Faculties and Abilities of thoſe whom he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in writing the Holy Scriptures.</hi> Their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Reaſon, Judgment, Memory, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections were all ſet on work, and did concur. He made uſe of their Heads and Hearts as well as Hands. So that they made uſe of their own Reaſon, Judgment and Underſtanding; as is undeniably evident from <hi>Luke</hi>'s <hi>Preface</hi> to his Goſpel, where the Examples of others was one (ſubordinate) Motive to engage him to write: <hi>Since many have taken in hand— it ſeemed good to me alſo</hi> — Luke 1.1-3. Yet withal, he was moved by the Holy Ghoſt alſo, ſo that he might have added (as the Councel of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did) It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and to me. So <hi>David's heart was inditing a good matter,</hi> Pſal. 45.1.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39375:17"/> And <hi>Peter</hi> upon conſideration of his ſudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, was careful to leave that in Writing which might be of uſe to 'em after his deceaſe, that they might <hi>have thoſe things always in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.14, 15,</p>
            <p>To this Head muſt be referr'd ſuch paſſages as theſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.28. <hi>When I have performed this, and have ſealed to them this fruit, I'll come by you into Spain.</hi> Theſe were his preſent thoughts; wherein yet it is ſuppoſed he was prevented by the Providence of God. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10. <hi>To the married I command; yet not I, but the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Heb. 13.22, 23. <hi>I beſeech you Brethren, ſuffer the word of Exhortation; for I have written a Letter to you in few words. Know ye that our brother Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy is ſet at liberty; with whom, if he come ſhortly, I will ſee you.</hi> 2 Cor. 11.17. <hi>That which I ſpeak, I ſpeak it not after the Lord, but as it were fooliſhly in this confidence of boaſting.</hi> V. 23. <hi>I ſpeak as a fool.</hi> So <hi>c.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>I knew a man in Chriſt — whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the body or out of the body, I cannot tell,</hi> &amp;c. Here the Holy Ghoſt directs <hi>Paul</hi> to ſpeak only his own thoughts and knowledge, without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting him whether it was <hi>in the Body or out of the Body.</hi> Thus every-where generally the Apoſtle ſpeaks all in his own Perſon, tho' with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al he aſſerts his having the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.-40. So that I ſay, There was a concurrence of both.</p>
            <p>And by this Aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, their natural Faculties were advanc'd and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd to the higheſt pitch (as will be ſeen more fully afterwards.) As <hi>Grace</hi> is ingrafted into and inoculated upon <hi>Nature</hi> to refine and perfect it, ſo this divine <hi>afflatus</hi> was ſuperadded to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Abilities to rectify and elevate 'em: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39375:18"/> in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Arguings every-where; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Romans, Galatians</hi> and <hi>Hebrews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">§. 16. Prop. V. <hi>As the Holy Ghoſt in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure of Scripture, made uſe of the Reaſon and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Pen-men, ſo He attemper'd and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated his Inſpiration to the particular genius of each Writer.</hi> Hereby it came to paſs, That the Liquor ſavour'd of the Pipe through which it ran. As God concurrs with all Creatures ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their particular Natures; with <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Agents</hi> Naturally; with <hi>Free Agents</hi> Volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily; ſo he did aſſiſt theſe Writers in a way ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their own natural Apprehenſions and Abilities; ſo that their <hi>Style</hi> and <hi>Language</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they clothed their Matter, was of the ſame Strain and <hi>Make</hi> with that which they uſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in expreſſing their own Conceptions by, upon other occaſions. Yet this muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood only for the <hi>generality;</hi> for doubtleſs upon ſome ſpecial Occaſions the Holy Ghoſt might ſuggeſt other <hi>Words,</hi> as well as <hi>Matter</hi> to 'em, than what they had been accuſtomed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> indeed ſeems to be otherwiſe mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That there was nothing of their own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>genius</hi> to be found in any of their Writings: for he expreſſes himſelf thus: <q rend="margQuotes">Neither has their ſucceſs been much better, who have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed their <hi>Critical Ability</hi> in judging of the <hi>Style</hi> of the particular Writers of the Scripture, preferring one <hi>before</hi> and <hi>above</hi> another; whereas the <hi>Style</hi> of every one of them is beſt ſuited to the <hi>ſubject Matter</hi> whereof he treats, and the <hi>End</hi> aimed at, and the <hi>Perſons</hi> with whom he had to do. And herein <hi>Jerom (Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39375:18"/> in Iſaiam &amp; Amoſum)</hi> has led the way to others, and drawn many into a common mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. The <hi>Style</hi> of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> he ſaith, is proper, <hi>urbane,</hi> high and excellent: but that of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea,</hi> and eſpecially of <hi>Amos,</hi> low, plain, <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper,</hi> ſavouring of the Country, and his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, who was a <hi>Shepherd.</hi> But thoſe that underſtand their <hi>Style</hi> and <hi>Language</hi> will not eaſily give conſent unto him, tho the report be commonly admitted by the moſt. It is true, there appears in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> an excellent <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his Exhortations, Expoſtulations and Comminations; attended with Efficacious <hi>Apoſtrophes, Proſopopaeiaes, Metaphors</hi> and <hi>Alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> a compacted Fulneſs in his Prophecies and Predictions, a ſweet <hi>Evangelical</hi> Spiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his Expreſſion of Promiſes, with fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Paranomoſiaes</hi> and <hi>Elleipſes,</hi> which have a ſpecial <hi>Elegancy</hi> in that Language; whence he is uſually inſtanc'd in by <hi>learned Men,</hi> as an <hi>Example</hi> of the <hi>Eloquence</hi> of the divine Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> preferr'd to that of <hi>Eſchines, Demoſthenes</hi> or <hi>Cicero.</hi> But the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der muſt take heed that he look not for the peculiar <hi>Excellencies</hi> of that Prophet abſolutely in the <hi>Words</hi> uſed by him, but rather in the <hi>Things</hi> that it pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt to uſe him as his Inſtrument in the Revelation of. But the other part of <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Cenſure is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly devoid of any good foundation. The <hi>Style</hi> of <hi>Amos,</hi> conſidering the <hi>ſubject Matter</hi> that he treats of, and the <hi>Perſons</hi> with whom he had to do, in ſuiting of Words and Speech, wherein all true <hi>ſolid Eloquence</hi> conſiſteth, is every way as proper, as <hi>Elegant</hi> as that of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> Neither will the knowing Reader find
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39375:19"/> him wanting in any of the Celebrated <hi>Styles</hi> of Writing, where occaſion unto them is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred.</q> Thus he. <hi>Exercit. on Ep. to</hi> Heb. <hi>Vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 15. §. 27.</p>
            <p>But that the Holy Ghoſt did thus accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date himſelf to the particular <hi>genius</hi> of the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, both as to <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Style,</hi> ſeems evident to me by divers inſtances; as of <hi>David,</hi> whoſe natural <hi>Inclination</hi> led him to <hi>Muſick,</hi> to which he was addicted from his Youth, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.18. and probably to <hi>Poeſy</hi> too, in regard of the near Affinity that is between 'em; and accordingly the Holy Ghoſt imploys him in compoſing and inditing of <hi>Pſalms:</hi> whence he was called <hi>The ſweet Pſalmiſt of Iſrael,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.-1. So <hi>Solomon,</hi> famous for <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> was uſed in Writing of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,</hi> wherein the Quinteſſence and Marrow of Wiſdom doth diſcover it ſelf: He likewiſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had the fulleſt <hi>Experience</hi> of the Vanity of all <hi>worldly Enjoyments</hi> that ever any one had, is imploy'd to write upon that Subject. So <hi>Paul,</hi> who was both a great <hi>Scholar,</hi> and wrapt up into the <hi>third Heaven,</hi> ſhows more <hi>Learning</hi> than any other of the Apoſtles, and alſo treats of the moſt ſublime and divine <hi>Myſteries</hi> of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>This likewiſe appears in the different<note n="*" place="margin">Praetereà ſcito unum quem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiare quid habere, &amp; in ca lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guâ, cáque loque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione quae ipſi eſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaris &amp; conſue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, ipſum impelli à Prophetiá ſuâ ad loquendum ei qui intelligit ipſum. <hi>Maim. More Nev. p. 11. c. 29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Styles</hi> of the <hi>Prophets. Eſay,</hi> a <hi>Courtier,</hi> writes in a lofty, elegant <hi>Style,</hi> embelliſhed with frequent <hi>Parano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſies. Jeremy</hi> writes in a more plain and eaſy <hi>Style. Ezekiel</hi> is full of <hi>Parables, Types, Allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> and <hi>Myſtical Repreſentations;</hi> which occaſion'd profane Spirits to ſcoff at him as an <hi>Enigmatical,</hi> obſcure Writer. <hi>c.</hi> 20. 49. <hi>Doth he not ſpeak Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles? Hoſea</hi>'s Style is very conciſe, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently obſcure.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:39375:19"/>
            <p>Now this difference cannot ariſe meerly from the difference of the <hi>Subjects</hi> (as I grant it muſt needs do in ſome caſes, viz. <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> and <hi>Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Writings) for the Prophecies of <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel;</hi> as they agree very much in reſpect of <hi>Time,</hi> ſo they do in <hi>Argument</hi> alſo: <hi>viz.</hi> To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Judgments againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> for their Sins, and particularly to fore-tell the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity for ſeventy years; as <hi>Jeremy</hi> doth: and alſo the Deſtruction of the Temple and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> does: And for <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm what <hi>Jeremy</hi> had deliver'd, and to Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy the ſame things (tho' more vehemently) in <hi>Chaldea,</hi> that <hi>Jeremy</hi> had done in <hi>Judea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that, I ſay, this difference of their <hi>Styles</hi> did not proceed either from the <hi>Subjects</hi> they wrote about, nor meerly from the Holy Ghoſt, but their own particular <hi>genius</hi> (moſtly) and way of Expreſſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I have premiſed by way of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction,</hi> to uſher in my main <hi>Deſign</hi> and Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which is to open the Nature of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, wherewith the Pen-men of the ſacred Oracles were aſſiſted in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Holy Scriptures: which I now enter upon in</p>
            <p n="17">§. 17. Prop. VI. <hi>The Inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt to the Pen-men of Scripture doth include and contain divers things in it.</hi> It does conſiſt of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Ingredients,</hi> as I may ſay. The Holy Ghoſt aſſiſted the Pen-men of Scripture ſeveral ways. His Agency herein may be laid out in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>He moved and ſtirr'd 'em up to write by a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Impulſe.</hi> He was the <hi>primum mobile</hi> that ſet all the Wheels a going. He call'd 'em into this Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39375:20"/> and ſet 'em all a work. This he did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by a particular, expreſs <hi>Command:</hi> as to <hi>Moſes</hi> to write ſeveral things, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.14. and 34.27. and to <hi>Jeremy,</hi> c. 30. 2. and 36. 2. and to <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 1.10: But moſt uſually by a ſtrong <hi>Impulſe</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) upon their Spirits, which effectually inclin'd, and diſpos'd 'em to the Work. He ſpake to 'em <hi>with a ſtrong hand,</hi> Eſa. 8.11. See <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.9.</p>
            <p>The Pen-man did not firſt reſolve and purpoſe with himſelf to write ſuch a Book (as in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Caſes) and then the Spirit did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as it is ſaid in another caſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.) No; this was not the <hi>Method:</hi> This is expreſsly denied, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>The prophecy came not in old time by the Will of Man.</hi> The <hi>Will of Man</hi> was not the firſt Mover, but the Spirit of God; as it follows there.</p>
            <p>True indeed, they made uſe of their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Reaſon (as I ſaid before,) <hi>It ſeemed good to me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Luke:</hi> And hence the Work wrought, or Effect produced was <hi>Theirs:</hi> called therefore <hi>The Goſpel of Matthew: The Epiſtle of Paul,</hi> &amp;c. But inaſmuch as they were therein aſſiſted by the Holy Ghoſt in thoſe ways and manners as are here laid down, the <hi>Work done</hi> may be alſo aſcribed to the Holy Ghoſt. And ſo it is <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſaith, To day if you will hear his voice,</hi> &amp;c. And of the Prophets in general it is ſaid, That <hi>the Spirit of God in them did ſignify</hi> ſuch and ſuch things, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. There was a Concurrence of both. So <hi>Mark</hi> 12.36. <hi>David himſelf ſaid by the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Holy Men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> As that which is dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by one, and written by another, the Work
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39375:20"/> may be aſcribed to both; to one as the <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal,</hi> to the other as the <hi>Inſtrumental Cauſe:</hi> Tho', I confeſs, this inſtance does not fully reach the Caſe, becauſe the Pen-men of Scripture had a greater ſhare in the Work than as meer <hi>Amanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſes,</hi> as was ſhow'd.</p>
            <p n="18">§. 18. 2. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt was their Task-maſter to ſet 'em their Tasks.</hi> He cut out every one's work for him. He appointed 'em their ſhare: aſſign'd 'em that <hi>Part</hi> and <hi>Province</hi> they were to adorn and cultivate. There was a great Work to be done; the perfect Revelation of the Will of God for our Salvation: divers <hi>Inſtructions</hi> and <hi>Directions</hi> to be given, ſome by one hand, ſome by another, to teach us how to govern our ſelves in our <hi>Way,</hi> till we arrive at our <hi>Journey's end:</hi> Much <hi>Proviſion</hi> of all ſorts, both for <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Phyſick</hi> was to be made: many <hi>Workmen</hi> to be imploy'd herein, who knew not each others Task: Therefore it was neceſſary there ſhould be one general <hi>Superviſor,</hi> or <hi>Overſeer,</hi> to aſſign to each one what his ſhare ſhould be; and that according to his particular <hi>Talent</hi> and <hi>Ability.</hi> As in the Parable of the Talents it is ſaid, The Owner of the Talents gave <hi>to every man according to his ſeveral ability,</hi> Matth. 25.15. So it was here. The Work of the <hi>ſweet Pſalmiſt of Iſrael,</hi> was to compoſe <hi>Pſalms:</hi> of the Wiſeſt of Men, to utter <hi>Proverbs:</hi> of that Apoſtle that was wrapt up into the third Heaven, and there heard <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>unutterable matters,</hi> to declare, both by <hi>Tongue</hi> and <hi>Pen,</hi> the deep things of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Election, Predeſtination, Juſtification;</hi> Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the natural Branches of the Olive, and ingrafting wild Branches into their room; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing the whole Frame of <hi>Moſaical Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:39375:21"/> opening the Nature of Chriſt's <hi>Prieſthood:</hi> ſhowing the Manner of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and the Nature of <hi>Spiritual</hi> Bodies, and the like.</p>
            <p n="19">§. 19. 3. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt aſſiſted the Pen-men of Scripture by way of Illumination of their Minds, whereby they had a diſtinct underſtanding of all thoſe Truths, whether Doctrinal or Practical, that were to be deliver'd by 'em.</hi> They ſaw all in a true and clear Light: and therefore they did not falter, or ſwerve in the leaſt from the truth in any point. They made no falſe ſteps, but were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, both from <hi>ſtumbling</hi> in the way, and <hi>ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping aſide</hi> out of it. Hence it comes to paſs, that all their <hi>Arguings</hi> are ſound and ſolid, and all their Inferences from Scripture or Reaſon, are well bottom'd.</p>
            <p n="20">§. 20. For the Pen-men of the <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> Parts of Scripture, this kind of Aſſiſtance does not ſo much belong unto them, becauſe their Writings contain, for the moſt part, only <hi>Matters of Fact,</hi> which are eaſily intelligible: and therefore I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this kind of Aſſiſtance chiefly to the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the <hi>Prophets</hi> (ſtrictly taken) and <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> Many things indeed in the Writings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are plain enough, the Subject of 'em being purely <hi>Practical;</hi> as <hi>Inſtructions</hi> to the People about their Duty, <hi>Reproof</hi> for their Sins, <hi>Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> of Mercy to the Penitent, <hi>Denunciations</hi> of Judgment againſt the Impenitent, and the like; and ſometimes alſo there are Matters <hi>Hiſtorical.</hi> And when among theſe, any thing was <hi>Parabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lically, Typically,</hi> or <hi>Myſtically</hi> repreſented, either they had a clear underſtanding of it themſelves, or the meaning of it was reveal'd to 'em by the Spirit of God: as we find in many inſtances: as, In thoſe Viſions of an <hi>Almond-tree,</hi> and a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39375:21"/> 
               <hi>Seething-pot, with the face towards the North,</hi> Jer. 1.11-16. So the Types of a <hi>linnen Girdle, and Bottles fill'd with Wine,</hi> were expounded, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.9-14. and in many other places of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy. The like was done to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> for his <hi>lying</hi> ſo many days <hi>upon his ſide, Ezek.</hi> 4.4-8. and to <hi>Amos</hi> c. 7. 7, 8. and 8. 2. <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.19, 21. and 4.11-14. and 5. 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">§. 21. Other things were <hi>Predictions</hi> of what was to come to paſs hereafter; and that either in a way of <hi>Judgment,</hi> as the Seventy years Captivity in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and many ſuch-like Evils: or in a way of <hi>Mercy,</hi> as their Return from <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon;</hi> and all thoſe Prophecies concerning Chriſt and his Kingdom, in the latter part of <hi>Eſay,</hi> and other places. Theſe they underſtood alſo, for the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of 'em, tho' poſſibly not every <hi>Circumſtance;</hi> for <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>They enquired and ſearched diligently about the Salvation they propheſied of, ſearching what, or what manner of time the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt which was in them did ſignify, when it teſtified before-hand the Sufferings of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.10, 11. However, I ſay, they underſtood at leaſt the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of their Prophecies; as appears by thoſe words <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.-1. <hi>A thing was revealed unto Daniel— and he underſtood the thing, and had underſtanding of the Viſion.</hi> See alſo <hi>c.</hi> 9. 22. and 10. 14. And when he did not underſtand ſome things, an Angel was employ'd to unfold the meaning of 'em to him: as <hi>c.</hi> 8. 15-19. and 12. 8, 11.</p>
            <p n="22">§. 22. Then for the Apoſtles, it is clear that the Holy Ghoſt did inable them fully to <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend,</hi> or at leaſt to <hi>Apprehend</hi> all thoſe Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion which they committed to Writing; as <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies of himſelf, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39375:22"/> 3, 4. <hi>How that by Revelation he made known unto me the myſtery, as I wrote before in few words, whereby, when ye read, ye may underſtand my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the myſtery of Chriſt.</hi> And it muſt needs be ſo; for</p>
            <p>This Aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to 'em by Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. <hi>When the ſpirit of truth is come, he will guide you into all truth; for he ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf; but whatſoever he ſhall hear, that ſhall he ſpeak, and he will ſhow you things to come:</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> 24.49. <hi>Behold I ſend the promiſe of my Father upon you.</hi> That Promiſe of the Father was the Holy Ghoſt; as appears by <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>And being aſſembled with them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them that they ſhould not depart from Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, but wait for the promiſe of the Father, which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ye have heard of me. For John truly bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with Water, but ye ſhall be baptized with the Holy Ghoſt not many days hence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">§. 23. Yet concerning this I obſerve, That this Knowledge was not communicated to 'em all at once, but by degrees: For (1.) They were train'd up in <hi>Chriſt's Family,</hi> and under the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of his continual Inſtructions. <hi>Mark</hi> 4.34. <hi>When they were alone, he expounded all things to his Diſciples.</hi> (2.) After his Reſurrection <hi>he expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to 'em in all the Scriptures the things concerning himſelf,</hi> Luke 24.27. (3.) After that, <hi>He open'd their Underſtandings to underſtand the Scriptures,</hi> v. 45. So that they could apply thoſe <hi>Scripture-Prophecies</hi> which concerned Chriſt, pertinently and patly, according to the true meaning of the Holy Ghoſt in 'em: and that beyond the firſt and immediate ſenſe of the words: as in that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 34.20. <hi>He keepeth all his bones: not one of 'em is broken:</hi> Wherein <hi>David</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:39375:22"/> ſeems to ſpeak only of Righteous men in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and of God's watchful Providence over 'em: (<hi>See</hi> Pool <hi>there:</hi>) but in <hi>John</hi> it's applied to that particular of <hi>Chriſt's bones</hi> not being broken, <hi>John</hi> 19.36. (4.) Some further degrees of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> or the Holy Ghoſt, were, doubtleſs, communicated to 'em, when Chriſt <hi>breathed on 'em, ſaying, Receive the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> John 20.22. (5.) Afterwards they were <hi>fill'd with the Holy Ghoſt</hi> on the day of Pentecoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4. And yet (6.) After that, They were further inſtructed in ſome particular Points: as <hi>Peter</hi> was concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Calling of the Gentiles,</hi> and the freedom of Converſation they might take with 'em, by <hi>Viſion, Acts</hi> 10.9-15. with <hi>v.</hi> 28, 34.</p>
            <p>By all which ways they were furniſh'd at length with ſuch a ſtock and treaſure of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Underſtanding, as might enable 'em both in <hi>Writing</hi> and <hi>Preaching</hi> to bring forth things <hi>new and old,</hi> Matth. 13.52. By theſe Ways, Steps and Methods, all the Myſteries of the Chriſtian Faith were fully and clearly revealed to the Apoſtles and Prophets of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.3-6.</p>
            <p n="24">§. 24. But as for <hi>Paul,</hi> it was otherwiſe with him. His Caſe was peculiar. He was not one of thoſe that <hi>accompanied with the reſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles all the time that the Lord Jeſus went in and out before 'em (Acts</hi> 1.21.) but was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.8.) an Abortive, a <hi>Caſtling,</hi> one <hi>born out of due time,</hi> not being called while Chriſt was upon Earth (as the other Apoſtles were) but was called in an extraordinary way by an immediate Voice from Heaven: therefore beſides that ſtock of common, <hi>natural Knowledge,</hi> which he acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his learned <hi>Education,</hi> it may ſeem that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39375:23"/> his <hi>ſupernatural Knowledge</hi> in all the Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion, was communicated to him all at once, when he was caught up into the third Heaven, whereby he was fill'd with a larger meaſure of the Spirit than the reſt of the Apoſtles: As appears both by his abundant <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> his abundant <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and his abundant <hi>Writings.</hi> (1.) His <hi>Labours</hi> were more abundant than the reſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. <hi>I laboured more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly than they all,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.23. <hi>In labours more abundant:</hi> Now <hi>Operari ſequitur eſſe.</hi> More <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> ſhows more <hi>Power.</hi> (2.) His <hi>Sufferings</hi> alſo were more abundant; of which he gives us a large Catalogue and Inventory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11-23-27. (3.) His <hi>Writings,</hi> and ſhare in the Canon of the New Teſtament, is far more than of any of the other Apoſtles. From all which we may fairly conclude, That he has a more abundant <hi>Glory</hi> than the reſt. For when <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto Chriſt, <hi>Behold, we have forſaken all, and followed thee: What ſhall we have?</hi> Chriſt thereupon replies, <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, that ye which have followed me in the regeneration, when the Son of Man ſhall ſit on the throne of his glory; ye alſo ſhall ſit on twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Iſrael: And every one that hath forſaken houſe, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my name's ſake, ſhall receive an hundred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, and inherit everlaſting life,</hi> Matth. 19.27-29. And again, When the Sons of <hi>Zebedee</hi> deſired to <hi>ſit, one on his right hand, and the other on his left in his Kingdom.</hi> Chriſt asks 'em, Whether they could <hi>drink of his cup, and be baptized with his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm? Mark</hi> 10.37, 38. implying, That the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Sufferers</hi> ſhall be the greateſt <hi>Gainers,</hi> and be moſt highly advanc'd in his Kingdom. Hence
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39375:23"/> then, I ſay, we may conclude, That ſince <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Sufferings</hi> (as well as his <hi>Labours</hi> and <hi>Writings</hi>) were the greateſt, That he ſhall not only ſit on a particular Throne, but on the higheſt Throne of all the Apoſtles, (and they were above all the Tribes,) and that he ſhall have the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the Univerſity of Heaven, as he was the higheſt Scholar in Chriſt's School on Earth. But this by the Bye.</p>
            <p n="25">§. 25. 4. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt aſſiſted the Pen-men of Scripture by ſtrengthning and refreſhing their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, to recollect and recall whatſoever they had ſeen or heard before, which He ſaw fit to be inſerted into their Writings.</hi> This kind of Aſſiſtance was afforded chiefly in relation to the <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> Parts of Scripture, wherein <hi>Matters of fact,</hi> which they had been <hi>Eye,</hi> or <hi>Ear-witneſſes</hi> of, are recorded. And this was expreſsly promis'd by Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 14.26. <hi>The Comforter ſhall come— who ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, whatſoever I have ſaid unto you:</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it was made good unto 'em, as we ſee in the Writings of the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a <hi>Narrative</hi> of the <hi>Birth, Life, Doctrine, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, Sufferings, Death, Reſurrection</hi> and <hi>Aſcenſion of Chriſt</hi> in an harmonious Diſcord.</p>
            <p>This was neceſſary for the Writers of all the <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> Parts of Scripture, that they might not be guilty of any omiſſion, or the leaſt miſtake, which would have defaced and fullied the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the whole, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.1.</p>
            <p n="26">§. 26. 5. <hi>He aſſiſted 'em by Directing 'em, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a Multitude of Matters of Fact, what to Omit, and what to Commit to Writing; and to make Choice of ſuch particulars, as he in his infinite Wiſdom ſaw fit to be left upon Record, for the uſe of ſucceeding
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39375:24"/> Generations.</hi> This is plain by thoſe paſſages, <hi>John</hi> 20.30, 31. <hi>Many other ſigns truly did Jeſus in the preſence of his Diſciples, which are not written in this book: but theſe things are written that you might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God, and that believing ye might have life through his Name:</hi> and 21. 25. <hi>There are alſo many other things which Jeſus did; the which, if they ſhould be written every one, I ſuppoſe that even the World it ſelf could not contain the books that ſhould be written.</hi> Now which of theſe were to be written, and which to be left unwritten; what might be of uſe, and what not, it was impoſſible for any humane Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to comprehend and determine; and therefore muſt be the work of the Holy Ghoſt. In general, <hi>All things were written for our Learning, Rom.</hi> 15.4. and <hi>Admonition,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.-11. and particularly, either as <hi>Sea-marks</hi> by way of <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to warn us to ſhun thoſe <hi>Rocks</hi> and <hi>Shelves</hi> which others had ſplit upon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6-10: or as <hi>Land-marks,</hi> to ſhow us how to ſteer our Courſe, that we may arrive ſafe in the Harbour of true Happineſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.-4. <hi>That we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope:</hi> or by way of Encouragement, to quicken us to the Performance of thoſe <hi>Duties,</hi> or Exerciſe of thoſe <hi>Graces,</hi> wherein the People of God in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times have been Eminent. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.23, 24. <hi>Now it was not written for his ſake alone that it was imputed to him; but for us alſo to whom it ſhall be imputed, if we believe on him,</hi> &amp;c. No <hi>humane Underſtanding</hi> could judge of theſe things; what was fit and uſeful, and what not; ſo that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Direction</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt was abſolutely neceſſary.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:39375:24"/>
            <p>And herein, among other particulars, his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was admirable in directing <hi>Moſes,</hi> in that compendious Hiſtory of things written by him, to record the Artifice of <hi>Jacob</hi> concerning the Sheep, <hi>Gen.</hi> 30. which may ſeem at firſt view to be beneath the Majeſty of the Holy Ghoſt, and Gravity of an inſpired Writer: But if it be well conſider'd, we may find that Excellent uſe may be made of it, to teach us how that the Providence of God is exerciſed over his Church and People (which was then confin'd within the bounds of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Family for the moſt part) for their <hi>Preſervation</hi> and <hi>Proviſion;</hi> and alſo, To warrant the uſe of <hi>natural means</hi> (ſuch as that was, at leaſt in part) in the purſuit of lawful Ends.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Direction</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to prevent ſtuffing their Writings with frivolous, and impertinent Stories, fabulous Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends, and <hi>Jewiſh Fables,</hi> wherewith their <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mud,</hi> and ſome of their <hi>Targums,</hi> and their <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſhim</hi> do abound: which therefore the Apoſtle cautions againſt, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4. and 4.7. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.14.</p>
            <p n="27">§. 27. 6. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt aſſiſted the Pen-men of Scripture, by exciting and calling forth thoſe</hi> Idea's <hi>and</hi> Images <hi>of things which were treaſur'd up in their Memories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it ſometimes comes to paſs in <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Preaching,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt brings into the Mind ſuch paſſages of Scripture, and other matters as are pertinent and ſuitable to the occaſion; tho' not with that <hi>Power, Evidence,</hi> and <hi>Infallibility</hi> which attended the divinely-inſpired Writers, but in a lower way; yet however it is ſomething of the ſame kind and nature.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:39375:25"/>
            <p>Hereby, tho' he did not ſuggeſt any <hi>new Matter,</hi> or Notion to 'em, which they knew not before; yet he brought ſuch things into their Minds, as by his infinite Wiſdom he ſaw meet to be made uſe of, to other ends and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes than the Pen-men were aware of, <hi>viz.</hi> for the <hi>Relief</hi> of the People of God upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in all their Doubts, Fears, and Troubles; and for <hi>Direction</hi> in all the <hi>Occurrences of life:</hi> hence proceed thoſe Multitudes of Directions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>particular Duties</hi> in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>All that Stock of <hi>habitual Knowledge,</hi> of what ſort ſoever, whether <hi>Natural, Acquired,</hi> or <hi>Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> wherewith they were furniſh'd before, was hereby <hi>educed,</hi> and <hi>reduced</hi> into Act, ſo far forth as was needful for the general Deſign of the Scripture, and there was occaſion for it. What they knew before, whether by the <hi>Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Study, Converſation,</hi> or <hi>divine Revelation,</hi> was all <hi>Materials</hi> for the Spirit to work <hi>upon,</hi> or <hi>with,</hi> in this way. As a <hi>Carpenter,</hi> when he builds a Houſe, chooſes out ſuch <hi>Timber, Stones,</hi> and other <hi>Materials,</hi> as are fit for his work, and lets the other alone: or, As a Phyſician chooſes out of the Apothecary's Shop ſuch <hi>Drugs</hi> and <hi>Medicines</hi> as are proper and ſuitable to his purpoſe, ſo did the Holy Ghoſt. We need not ſay that the Spirit did teach, or infuſe into 'em (whiſper in their Ears, as <hi>La Mothe</hi> expreſſes it) any thing which they knew before, but only called forth, propoſed and repreſented to their Minds ſuch of thoſe things which he found there, and would have made uſe of.</p>
            <p>Hence it came to paſs that <hi>Paul,</hi> the moſt learned of the Apoſtles, makes ſuch uſe of his <hi>Learning</hi> in his Writings, which is not to be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39375:25"/> found in the Writings of any other of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: As when he quotes ſome Sayings of the Heathen Poets: Of <hi>Aratus,</hi> in his diſcourſe to the Learned <hi>Athenians,</hi> Acts 17.-28. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Of <hi>Menander,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.33. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Of <hi>Epimenides,</hi> Tit. 1.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Spirit of God could have infuſed ſuch Notions into the other Apoſtles (as he enabled 'em to ſpeak with Tongues which they never learned) by infuſing the <hi>Idea's</hi> of all thoſe Languages in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Minds) but he made uſe only of ſuch things as he found in 'em (as to this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.)</p>
            <p>And herein, I take it, does chiefly conſiſt the <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Influence</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt in the Inditement of the greateſt part of Scripture. All the <hi>Hiſtorical, Dogmatical, Doctrinal,</hi> and <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Parts of Scripture owe their Original to this Work of the Holy Ghoſt: his calling forth ſuch and ſuch <hi>Matter,</hi> and <hi>Words,</hi> as ſhould be fit for the <hi>Edification</hi> and <hi>Inſtruction</hi> of the People of God in all generations. And hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</p>
            <p n="28">§. 28. 7. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt aſſiſted the Pen-men of Scripture by immediate ſuggeſting and dictating to 'em, and imprinting on their Minds all ſuch things as were matters of pure Revelation: i. e.</hi> That could not be known by 'em no otherwiſe than by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation: as, All things <hi>Paſt,</hi> of which there was neither <hi>Tradition</hi> nor <hi>Record.</hi> Such things <hi>Preſent,</hi> as either they had never heard of, or were without the reach of <hi>Man</hi>'s Knowledge: as the <hi>Thoughts, Deſires, Purpoſes, Inclinations,</hi> and <hi>Sincerity</hi> of the Heart, which are often declared in Scripture. And likewiſe <hi>things to Come,</hi> the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39375:26"/> Fore-telling whereof God challenges to himſelf as his <hi>peculiar Prerogative, Eſa.</hi> 46.9, 10. and 41. 22, 23. and 45.21.</p>
            <p>And here come in, under this Head of <hi>Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> all the <hi>Prophecies, Promiſes, Threatnings</hi> which lie ſcatter'd up and down throughout the whole Book of God. Theſe are granted by all (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept abſolute Antiſcripuriſts) to be of <hi>divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration</hi> in the ſtricteſt and moſt proper ſenſe, and the immediate Dictates of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="29">§. 29. 8. <hi>Beſides the particular Scope of each Book, and the Pen-men thereof, the Spirit of God had moreover a general and tranſcendent Super-intendency and Inſpection reaching over the whole; viz.</hi> To make it a compleat, perfect Canon and Rule both of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Life;</hi> containing all the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda, Agenda, Petenda,</hi> and <hi>Speranda,</hi> that ſo the <hi>Man of God might be perfect, throughly furniſht to every good work.</hi> This was that which could never come within the Compaſs of any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Writer's aim, but was the Work of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the whole: That every one ſhould write <hi>what,</hi> and <hi>ſo much</hi> as the Spirit ſaw fit: Every one ſhould caſt in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his Morſel or Share (as it's ſaid of the Apoſtles in the <hi>Creed,</hi>) ſo that all together it might be a perfect Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Will of God for the Uſe of the Church, the Body of Chriſt: That it ſhould contain all things neceſſary to Salvation, and whatſoever was <hi>profitable for Doctrine, for Reproof, for Correction, and for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.16, 17.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the Sixth Propoſition, ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeveral Branches, or Ways whereby the Holy Ghoſt aſſiſted the Pen-men of Scripture;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39375:26"/> from all which I may well conclude in the laſt Place,</p>
            <p n="30">§. 30. Prop. VII. <hi>The whole Scripture, both in reſpect of Matter and Words, is of divine Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> This ſeems to me to be a plain and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſequence of the foregoing Diſcourſe, That both <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Words</hi> were equally under the <hi>Direction</hi> and <hi>Influence</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt: Both of 'em had an equal ſhare in his <hi>Inſpiration</hi> in the ways fore-mention'd. Such <hi>Words,</hi> as well as <hi>Matter,</hi> were brought into their Minds, as the Holy Ghoſt thought fit. This is denied by <hi>La Mothe, part</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. tho' he grants ſomething like it. C. 5. §. 3. <hi>p.</hi> 120. where he ſaith, <hi>The Words and the Things depend upon one and the ſame ſort of Inſpiration: both the one and the other proceed from the ſame Spring, and are guided by the ſame Hand: They proceed equally from humane Faculties, and are equally directed by the Spirit of God</hi> — §. 31. The Apoſtle ſeems to ſpeak expreſly to this point, concerning the <hi>Words,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Which things alſo we ſpeak, not in the Words which man's Wiſdom teacheth, but which the Holy Ghoſt teacheth.</hi> Now, if it were ſo with 'em in their <hi>Speaking,</hi> much more in their <hi>Writing</hi> (if it be not all one, and he does not mean the ſame thing: concerning which <hi>ſee above,</hi> Prop. I. n. 1.) becauſe their <hi>Writing</hi> was of larger Extent than their <hi>Preaching, viz.</hi> for the Uſe of the Church in all Ages. Many paſſages alſo in the Scripture ſeem to look this way, and to imply as much. As, (1.) Thoſe general Words, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God,</hi> muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſignify more than a bare <hi>Direction</hi> (ſuch as <hi>La Mothe</hi> aſſerts, <hi>p.</hi> 121. <hi>He lets 'em alone when they go right; and when they are about to miſcarry,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39375:27"/> he brings 'em back again,) viz.</hi> an immediate <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe</hi> in thoſe ways that have been mention'd. So when the ſacred Pen-men thereof are ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>born up, carried above</hi> and beyond themſelves, to <hi>ſpeak his Words, and what he endited to 'em.</hi> Owen <hi>of Commun. p.</hi> 284. (2.) It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears alſo by thoſe words of <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.2. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord ſpake by me, and his Word was in my Tongue.</hi> He does not ſay, He ſpake by the Spirit, but the <hi>Spirit by him.</hi> The Spirit was the <hi>Principal Agent,</hi> he but the <hi>Inſtrument.</hi> Whereas, If the Spirit only directed him in what he wrote, then he was the <hi>Principal,</hi> and the Spirit only the <hi>Subordinate.</hi> Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s Note upon theſe Words is this: <q>The following Words, and conſequently the other Words and Pſalms, compoſed and utter'd by me upon the like ſolemn Occaſions, are not to be lookt upon as my private Fancies, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Inventions, but both the Matter and Words of 'em are ſuggeſted and govern'd by God's Spirit, which is the great Teacher of the Church.</q> (3.) The Places following ſeem alſo to ſpeak thus much. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.70. <hi>He ſpake by the mouth of his holy Prophets.</hi> Acts 4.25. <hi>Who by the mouth of thy holy ſervant David haſt ſaid.</hi> Mark 12.36. <hi>David</hi> himſelf ſaid by the Holy Ghoſt, and more expreſly <hi>Acts</hi> 1.16.— <hi>Which the Holy Ghoſt by the mouth of David ſpake before:</hi> and 28. 25. <hi>Well ſpake the Holy Ghoſt by Eſay the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</hi> Heb. 1.1. <hi>God ſpake in the Prophets:</hi> and 3.7. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſaith, To day if you will hear his voice,</hi> &amp;c. What can be more expreſs than theſe places? A bare <hi>Guidance</hi> and <hi>Direction</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly will never comprehend the full Extent and Senſe of theſe Expreſſions. Sure God and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39375:27"/> the Holy Ghoſt cannot be ſaid to ſpeak <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> the Pen-men, except the very <hi>Words</hi> they ſpake and wrote were more than their own.</p>
            <p n="32">§. 32. And of this Judgment are many wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Divines, and learned Men, whoſe Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies I could produce: but I ſhall content my ſelf with two Eminent ones; the one a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, the other a Papiſt. The former is the Induſtrious, Judicious <hi>Pool,</hi> in his incomparable Annotations. <hi>Theſe words, He keeps all his bones,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>tho' here ſpoken of righteous Men in general, of whom they are true in a Metaphorical ſenſe; yet they have a further meaning in 'em, being dictated by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, (which dictated to</hi> David <hi>not only the Matter, but very Words and Expreſſions) to ſignify a great Myſtery, That none of Chriſt's bones ſhould be broken.</hi> Pool <hi>on</hi> Pſal. 34.20. The other is of <hi>Eſtius,</hi> an Excellent <hi>Commentator, Rectè igitur &amp; veriſſimè ex hoc loco ſtatuitur omnem Scripturam ſacram &amp; canonicam Spiritu ſancto dictante eſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptam; ità nimirum ut non ſolum ſententiae, ſed &amp; verba ſingula, &amp; verborum ordo; ac tota diſpoſitio ſit à Deo, tanquam per ſemetipſum loquente aut ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bente.</hi> Eſt. <hi>in</hi> 2 Tim. 3.16. <hi>From this place</hi> (2 Tim. 3.16.) <hi>it is well and rightly gather'd, that all the Holy, Canonical Scripture, was written by the dictate of the Holy Spirit; inſomuch that not only the Sentences, but the very Words, and the Order of the Words, and the whole diſpoſal is from God, as if it were ſpoken or written by Himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">§. 33. Now, from the foregoing Diſcourſe, we may gather what was the peculiar diſtinct Part and Share both of the <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> Cauſes of the Scripture; (which was, That that I deſign'd and aim'd at at firſt to find out and diſcover.) The Holy Ghoſt firſt ſet the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39375:28"/> Pen-men of Scripture a work, and <hi>moved</hi> 'em to write: He ſet 'em their <hi>Task,</hi> and appointed every one his <hi>Share,</hi> and that according to their ſeveral <hi>Abilities:</hi> He furniſht 'em with <hi>Matter</hi> for their Work, by <hi>Enlightning</hi> their Minds to <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> all their Work; <hi>Strengthning</hi> their <hi>Memories</hi> to recal what was neceſſary; <hi>Directing</hi> 'em what <hi>Matters</hi> to make choice of; <hi>Exciting</hi> and Calling forth into Act ſo much of what they knew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as was to be committed to Writing by 'em; <hi>Suggeſting</hi> to 'em, and <hi>Imprinting</hi> upon their Minds ſuch things as they knew not, but were Matters of <hi>pure Revelation;</hi> Providing that the whole ſhould be a perfect Rule both of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Life.</hi> In theſe ſeveral Particulars, I conceive, with Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, the <hi>Inſpiration,</hi> and <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt to the Pen-men of Scripture did conſiſt. This was <hi>His Part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then for the <hi>Pen-men</hi> themſelves, their own <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> did concur in all they wrote: <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Heart indited a good Matter,</hi> Pſal. 45.1. <hi>David</hi> himſelf ſpake, <hi>Mark</hi> 12.36. <hi>It ſeemed good to</hi> Luke <hi>to write,</hi> Luke 1.3. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpake generally in their own Perſons. Hence the <hi>Work done</hi> is very properly aſcribed to both: To the Holy Ghoſt as the <hi>Principal</hi> Author and Efficient; to the <hi>Holy Men of God,</hi> as <hi>Inſtruments</hi> imploy'd by Him, and in Subordination to Him, to be the immediate Authors of the Writings compoſed by them.</p>
            <p>This is what I have to offer in this Point: wherein if there be any thing found which may be uſeful, and ſhall approve it ſelf to the godly judicious, let God have the Glory; by whoſe Aſſiſtance alone this hath been begun, carried on, and brought to</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.94/5.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:39375:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
